Because I usually take the role of trying to explain to people how wonderful the new
technologies that are coming along are going to be. And I thought that since I was among
friends here, I would tell you what I really think. And try to look back and try to understand
what is really going on here with these amazing jumps in technology. It seems so fast that
we can barely keep on top of it. So I'm going to start out by showing just one very boring
technology slide. And then, so if you can just turn on the slide that's on. This is
just a random slide that I picked out of my file. And what I want to show you is not so
much the details of this slide, but the general form of it. This happens to be a slide of
some analysis that we were doing about the power of risk microprocessors versus the power
of local area networks. And the interesting thing about it is that this slide, like so
many technology slides that we're used to, is a sort of a straight line on a semi-log
curve. In other words, every step here represents an order of magnitude and performance gain.
And we're sort of the, this is a new thing that we talk about technology on semi-log
curve. Something really weird is going on here. And that's basically what I'm going
to be talking about. So if you bring up the lights. If you could bring up the lights higher
because I'm just going to use a piece of paper here. Now, why do we draw technology curves
on semi-log curves? Well, the answer is if I drew it on a normal curve, where let's say
this is years, this is time of some sort, and this is whatever measure of the technology
that I'm trying to graph, the graphs look sort of silly. They sort of go like this.
And they don't tell us much. Now, if I graph, for instance, some other technology, say transportation
technology, on a semi-log curve, it would look very stupid. It would look like a flat
line. But when something like this happens, things are qualitatively changing. So if transportation
technology was moving along as fast as microprocessor technology, then sort of day after tomorrow
I would be able to get in a taxi cab and be in Tokyo in 30 seconds. It's not moving like
that. And there's nothing precedented in the history of technology development of this
kind of self-feeding growth where you go by orders of magnitude every few years. Now,
the question that I'd like to ask is if you look at these exponential curves, they don't
go on forever. Things just can't possibly keep changing as fast as they are. One of
two things is going to happen. Either it's going to turn into sort of classical S-curve
like this until something totally different comes along. Or maybe it's going to do this.
That's about all it can do. Now, I'm an optimist, so I sort of think it's probably going to
do something like that. If so, that means that what we're in the middle of right now
is a transition. We're sort of on this line in a transition from the way that the world
used to be to some new way that the world is. And so what I'm trying to ask, and I've
been asking myself, is what's this new way that the world is? What's the new state that
the world is heading toward? Because the transition seems very, very confusing when we're right
in the middle of it. Now, when I was a kid growing up, the future was kind of the year
2000. And people used to talk about what would happen in the year 2000. Now, here's a conference
in which people talk about the future. And you notice that the future is still at about
the year 2000. That's about as far as we go out. So, in other words, the future has kind
of been shrinking one year per year for my whole lifetime. Now, I think that the reason
is, is because we all feel that something's happening there. That transition is happening.
We can all sense it. And we know that it just doesn't make too much sense to think out 30,
30, 50 years. Because everything's going to be so different that a simple extrapolation
of what we're doing just doesn't make any sense at all. So, what I would like to talk
about is what that could be, what that transition could be that we're going through. Now, in
order to do that, I'm going to have to talk about a bunch of stuff that really has nothing
to do with technology and computers. Because I think the only way to understand this is
to really step back and take a long time scale look at things. So, the time scale that I
would like to look at this on is the time scale of life on Earth. So, I think this picture
makes sense if you look at it a few billion years at a time. So, if you go back about
two and a half billion years, the Earth was this big, sterile hunk of rock with a lot
of chemicals floating around on it. And if you look at the way that the chemicals got
organized, we begin to get a pretty good idea of how they do it. And I think that there's
theories that are beginning to understand about how it started with RNA. But I'm going
to tell a sort of simple story of it, which is that at that time there were little drops
of oil floating around with all kinds of different recipes of chemicals in them. And some of
those drops of oils had a particular combination of chemicals in them, which caused them to
incorporate chemicals from the outside and grow the drops of oil. And those that were
like that started to split and divide. And those were the most primitive forms of cells
in a sense, those little drops of oil. But now, those drops of oil weren't really life
as we say it now because every one of them was a little random recipe of chemicals. And
sometime it divided something different. I mean, it got sort of unequal division of
the chemicals within it. And so every drop was a little bit different. In fact, the drops
that were different in a way that caused them to be better at incorporating chemicals around
them grew more, incorporated more chemicals, and divided more. So those tended to live
longer, get expressed more. Now, that's sort of just a very simple chemical form of life.
But when things got interesting was when these drops learned a trick of abstraction. Somehow,
by ways that we don't quite understand, these little drops learned to write down information.
They learned to record the information that was the recipe of the cell onto a particular
kind of chemical called DNA. So in other words, they worked out in this sort of mindless evolutionary
way a form of writing that let them write down what they were so that that way of writing
it down could get copied. The amazing thing is that that way of writing seems to have
stayed steady since it evolved two and a half billion years ago. In fact, the recipe for
us, our genes is exactly that same code in that same way of writing. In fact, every living
creature is sort of written in exactly the same set of letters in the same code. In fact,
one of the things that I did just for amusement purposes is we can now write things in this
code. And I've got here a little 100 micrograms of white powder, which I try not to let the
security people see at airports. But this has in it, what I did is I took this code.
The code has standard letters that we use for symbolizing it. And I wrote my business
card onto a piece of DNA and amplified it 10 to the 22 times. So if anyone would like
100 million copies of my business card, I have money for everyone in the room, and in
fact everyone in the world. And it's right here. So if I had really been an egotist,
I would have put it into a virus and released it in the room. So what was the next step?
Writing down the DNA was an interesting step. And that caused these cells to, that kept
them happy for another billion years. But then there was another really interesting
step where things became completely different, which is these cells started exchanging and
communicating information so that they began to get communities of cells. I don't know
if you know this, but bacteria can actually exchange DNA. That's why, for instance, antibiotic
resistance has evolved. Some bacteria figured out how to stay away from psilon, and it went
around sort of trading its little DNA information with other bacteria, and now we have a lot
of bacteria that are resistant to psilon because bacteria communicate. Now what this communication
allowed was communities to form that in some sense were in the same boat together. They
were synergistic. So they survived or they failed together, which means that if a community
was very successful, all the individuals in that community were repeated more, and they
were favored by evolution. Now the transition point happened when these communities got
so close that in fact they got together and decided to write down the whole recipe for
the community together on one string of DNA. And so the next stage that's interesting
in life took about another billion years. And at that stage, we have multicellular communities,
communities of lots of different types of cells working together as a single organism.
And in fact, we're such a multicellular community. We have lots of cells that are not out for
themselves anymore. Your skin cell is really useless without a heart cell, a muscle cell,
a brain cell, and so on. So these communities began to evolve so that the interesting level
on which evolution was taking place was no longer a cell, but a community which we call
an organism. Now the next step that happened is within these communities, these communities
of cells again began to abstract information. And they began building very special structures
that did nothing but process information within the community. And those are the neural structures.
So neurons are the information processing apparatus of those communities of cells built
up. And in fact, they began to get specialists in the community in special structures that
were responsible for recording, understanding, learning information. And that was the brains
and the nervous system of those communities. And that gave them an evolutionary advantage
because at that point, an individual, things, learning could happen within the time span
of a single organism instead of over this evolutionary time span. So an organism could
for instance learn not to eat a certain kind of fruit because it tasted bad and it got
sick last time it ate it. That could happen within the lifetime of a single organism whereas
before they had built those special information processing structures, that would have had
to be learned evolutionarily over hundreds of thousands of years by the individuals dying
off today that kind of fruit. So that nervous system, the fact that they built those special
information structures tremendously speeded up the whole process of evolution because
evolution could now happen within an individual. It could happen in learning time scale. Then
what happened was the individuals worked out, of course, tricks of communicating. And
for example, the most sophisticated version that we're aware of is human language. It's
really a pretty amazing invention if you think about it. Here I have a very complicated messy
confused idea in my head. I'm sitting here making grunting sounds basically and hopefully
constructing a similar messy confused idea in your head that bears some analogy to it.
So we're taking something very complicated, turning it into sound, sequence of sounds
and producing something very complicated in your brain. So this allows us now to begin
to start functioning as a single organism. And so in fact what we've done is we, humanity,
have started abstracting out, we're going through the same levels that multicellular
organisms have gone through, abstracting out our methods of recording, presenting, processing
information. So for example, the invention of language was a tiny step in that direction.
Telephony, computers, videotapes, CD-ROMs, so on are all our specialized mechanisms that
we've now built within our society for handling that information. And it all connects us together
into something that is much bigger and much faster and able to evolve than what we were
before. So now evolution can take place on the scale of microseconds. And you saw Kai's
little evolutionary example where he sort of did a little bit of evolution of a convolution
program right before your eyes. So now we've speeded up the timescales once again. So the
first steps of the story that I told you about took a billion years of peace. And the next
steps like nervous systems and brains took a few hundred million years. And the next
steps like language and so on took less than a million years. And these next steps like
electronics seems to be taking only a few decades. And the process is feeding on itself
and becoming I guess autocatalytic is the word for it. When something reinforces its
rate of change, the more it changes the faster it changes. And I think that that's what we're
seeing here in this explosion of curve. We're seeing this process feeding back on itself.
Now I design computers for a living. And I know the mechanisms that I use to design computers
would be impossible without recent advances in computers. So right now what I do is I
design objects at such complexity that it's really impossible for me to design them in
the traditional sense. I don't know what every transistor in a connection machine does. There
are billions of them. Instead what I do and what the designers at Thinking Machines do
is we think at some level of abstraction and then we hand it to the machine and the machine
takes it beyond what we could ever do. Much farther and faster than what we could ever
do. And in fact sometimes it takes it by methods that we don't quite even understand. One method
that's particularly interesting that I've been using a lot lately is evolution itself.
So what we do is we put inside the machine a process of evolution that takes place on
the microsecond time scale. So for example in the most extreme cases we can actually
evolve a program by starting out with random sequences of instructions. Say computer would
you please make a hundred million random sequences of instructions. Now would you please run
all of those random sequences of instructions, run all of those programs and pick out the
ones that came closest to do what I wanted. So in other words I define what I wanted.
Let's say I want to sort numbers as a simple example I've done. So find the programs that
come closest to sorting numbers. So of course random sequences of instructions are very
unlikely to sort numbers. So none of them will really do it. But one of them by luck
may put two numbers in the right order. And I say to the computer would you please now
take the 10% of those random sequences that did the best job, save those, kill off the
rest and now let's reproduce the ones that sorted numbers the best. And let's reproduce
them by a process of recombination analogous to sex. Take two programs and they produce
children by exchanging their subroutines and the children inherit the traits, the subroutines
of the two programs. So I've got now a new generation of programs that are produced by
combinations of the programs that did a little bit better job. Say please repeat that process,
score them again, introduce some mutations perhaps and try that again and do that for
another generation. Well every one of those generations just takes a few milliseconds.
So I can do the equivalent of millions of years of evolution on that within the computer
in a few minutes or in the complicated cases in a few hours. At the end of that I end up
with programs that are absolutely perfect at sorting numbers. In fact they are programs
that are much more efficient than programs I could have ever written by hand. Now if
I look at those programs I can't tell you how they work. I've tried looking at them
and tell you how they work. They're obscure, weird programs. But they do the job and in
fact I know I'm very confident that they do the job because they come from a line of hundreds
of thousands of programs that did the job. In fact their life depended on doing the job.
I was writing in a 747 with Marvin Minsky once and he pulls out this card and he said
oh look, look at this, it says this plane has hundreds of thousands of tiny parts working
together to make you a safe flight. Doesn't that make you feel confident? In fact we know
that the engineering process doesn't work very well when it gets complicated. So we're
beginning to depend on computers to do a process that's very different than engineering. And
it lets us produce things of much more complexity than normal engineering lets us produce. And
yet we don't quite understand the objects of it. So in a sense it's getting ahead of
us. We're now using those programs to make much faster computers so that we'll be able
to run this process much faster. So it's feeding back on itself. The thing is becoming faster
and that's why I think it seems so confusing because all of these technologies are feeding
back on themselves. We're taking off. And what we are is we're at a point in time which
is analogous to when single cell organisms were turning into multi cell organisms. So
we're the amoebas and we can't quite figure out what the hell this thing is we're creating.
We're right at that point of transition. But I think that there really is something coming
along after us. I think it's very haughty of us to think that we're the end product
of evolution. And I think all of us here are a part of producing whatever that next thing
is. So lunch is coming along and I think I will stop at that point before I get selected
out.